Guide to the Imre Forbáth diaries,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Imre Forbáth Diaries, 1900-1943
  - Journal 12: November 7, 1924 to May 17, 1927 (Box 2)
    The Carbamide Syndicate in Vienna talks about the Egyptian market. The world’s companies agree to establish the Fertilizer Sales Company, located in London. In half a year, a world organization is formed, originally established to fight the Americans, but in the end unable to do without American funds. The Cartel opens a common sales office in Rotterdam.
    Forbáth’s business is a success; the Nitrogen Factory has been consolidated, and half of all the production for the next five years has been sold. In addition to the Syndicate, the company makes Romanian, Hungarian, Czechoslovak, Italian, and Greek sales.
    Forbáth’s other great business success is the sale of the Szurdics brick factory. He wants to start a new private engineering practice again, so he applies to the Engineers’ Chamber. He is asked to take on the directorship of the Hungarian Commerce Bank, but he turns it down.
    He talks with O’Daniel and Strowell about an American loan and cooperation with the New York cyanide factory. He is thinking about selling shares.
    Adolf, Otto
    Alpar, Ignac
    Angello
    August Weyl (Dr.)
    Averescu
    Banki, Donath
    Barnauer
    Beothy, Laszlo
    Beregi, Bela
    Bratianu
    Buch
    Buchler
    Caro
    Caso, Ratz
    Chatel
    Colener
    Constantinidis, Peter
    Cox
    Csosz, Imre
    Decsey, Toni
    Dimitrescu
    Doroki, Ervin
    Endrody, Gyula
    Frang (Professor)
    Gisser, Gyula
    Grant, Thorn
    Haining
    Harkanyy
    Hevesy, Rabbi
    Hevesy, Sandor
    Hopfgartner
    Horvath, Lipot
    Kefener
    Kovacs, Sebestyen Aladar
    Krapner
    Kraszaer
    Lansky
    Lichermann (Dr.)
    Lorant
    Malinoff
    Mangold (Dr.)
    Nane
    O’Daniel
    Odon Stern (Dr.)
    Pasons
    Patak
    Popoch
    Prasole
    Preszlenyi, Aladar
    Reiter
    RicardoJualino
    Roddling
    Rosenbaum
    Salusinszky, Ruttai
    Sanor, Pal
    Simko
    Simonovits
    Srazil
    Stem, Odon (Dr.)
    Strettler
    Strowell
    Tagore, Mahalanobil Rabindranat
    Terrace
    Thomanek
    Thomond, Erno
    Tolnay
    Torok, Éva
    Vajda, György (Dr.)
    Vajda-Vacood, Sandor
    Vanyi, Dezso
    Vida
    Volentine
    Weinstein, Lazari
    Wolf, Ulman
    Zielinszky, Szilard
    Wohnungsbauten der Stadt Wien (Building of Apartments in Vienna), Lloyd
    Water Supply of the Goldberger Factory in Obuda
    Canalization of Szeged
  - Journal 13: May 18, 1927 - February 29, 1929 (Box 2)
    The international nitrogen market is in depression. The Bayerische Stickstoffwerke and the Aluminium Company leave the Cartel. Imre Forbáth renews the Nitrogen Factory’s contract with the Fertilizer Sale Company in Paris for an additional ten years, with new conditions. The Nitrogen Factory itself will no longer export, except to Hungary, Romania, and Czechoslovakia. In Trieste, the Sulfide’s director wants to buy the new electrode method used in Diciosanmartin. The factory’s engineer, Andor Leopold, asserts that the method is his property, and licenses it in his own name. The factory signs a contract with him. Ferdinand, King of Romania, dies. A series of changes occurs in the Romanian government. Manoilescu is tried on charges of intriguing for Prince Carol to become king, but is acquitted. The Romanian ministry demands money from the Nitrogen Factory, but Forbáth proves, using old records, that the previous Romanian government actually owed money to the Company. He collects the money from the new Ministry of War. Two Dutch creditors take over the Szurdics Factory. A new idea arises: licensing the Nitrogen Factory as a Hungarian-Romanian joint company, with the Romanian half under the control of the Ministry of War. In 1927, there are widespread strikes in Vienna to protest the verdict in the Schattendorf trial. Forbáth is in Vienna at the time street violence breaks out.
    In 1928, Lajos Hatvany returns to Hungary from exile by his own choice. He is put on trial for articles he wrote from 1920 to 1922, published in the Jövő in Vienna. He receives seven years imprisonment, and a 50,000 pengő fine.
    Imre Forbáth finds a Mátyás Codex miniature in a library in Brussels. He writes a letter to Petropavlovsk, where his fellow ex-prisoners of war left his papers. In 1928, he writes the story of his Siberian captivity, and binds it with a few photographs and a Bible from Siberia. He gives it to his son, Tamás, as a present.
    Balog
    Blytka
    Bralianu
    Constantinidis
    Drachler
    Egry, Aurel
    Gaal, Mozes
    Greiner, Colos and Hugo
    Jacoby, Andor (Dr.)
    Kornfeld (Count)
    Rohonyi
    Simontsich
    Stein ,Emil
    Stern, Gyula
    Szitovszky
    Tilny
    Torok, Emil
    Vida, Jeno
    Weiss, Fulop
    Wilchelm, Karoly (Dr.)
    "Diary of a Prisoner of War" (about the history of his Siberian captivity and his escape)
    Goldberger Factory in Obuda
    Wespag Textile Mill
  - Journal 14: February 15, 1929 - October 27, 1930 (Box 3)
    In the nationalization trial, the Nitrogen Company of Diciosanmartin stands against the Romanian Ministry of Interior Affairs. The question in dispute is whether there is a successor to the Austro-Hungarian Ministry of War. Forbáth learns that the Austro-Hungarian Ministry of War still exists in Vienna as a liquidation authority; therefore, there is no successor. The defense bases its case on this fact. The trial takes much time and energy, but on the first degree, the court decides in Forbáth’s favor. Manoilescu wants to get rid of all the Hungarian owners. The concerned parties begin to discuss the possibility of Romania buying out the Hungarians’ shares in the company.
    The structure of the company, including its liaison with the Romanian government, is so efficient that Imre Forbáth is able to direct affairs from his office in Budapest. Forbáth continues to be the international representative of the Nitrogen Factory. He goes to international Cartel and Syndicate meetings in Munich, Berlin, Hamburg, Dortmund, Paris, Strasbourg, Vienna, and Bucharest. The Nitrogen Pact of August 1930 is the biggest industrial pact ever at the time
    The Romanian and Russian gas industries are beginning to advance greatly.
    Zeppelins land in Budapest. The International Building Conference and Fair, the Nurnberg Fair, and the Poster Fair open in Budapest. A competition is announced for the planning of Erzsébet Boulevard and for the statue of István Tisza. On Saint Imre Day, the Ecclesiastical History Show opens. After the ceremony, large numbers of people want to protest against unemployment, but the government prohibits the demonstration by the time the workers arrive on the streets. The Social-Democratic leadership demonstrates its power.
    The Hungarian nitrogen market drops fifty percent due to the hardships of Hungarian agriculture. The Nitrogen Factory hands over Hungarian sales to the Szuperfoszfat Company, which is now under the direction of Krapner, also a director of the Nitrogen Factory. There is a discussion with a Swiss group about the possibility of selling the Nitrogen Factory.
    Forbáth’s construction plans for Bratislava win an international prize. All the newspapers write about Imre Forbáth winning his eighth international prize. Dr. Antal Szego wants to publish the biographies of the three hundred most important Hungarian Jews in the fiftieth edition of the magazine Egyenloseg. Imre Forbáth would be one of them.
    Balla, Pal
    Berczely
    Bernhardt, Tibor
    Berta
    Bodnar
    Boila
    Bonis, Feri
    Botka
    Brunovszky, Pal
    Christescu, Vitnile
    Csaszkoczy
    Danken
    Davidis
    Delen
    Deutsch, Lajos
    Dierbauer, Vigil
    Dindra
    Dori, Otto
    Dragominescu
    Duzy
    Ehrensperger
    Elias
    Farago
    Farkas, Arpad
    Fischer, Erno (Dr.)
    Fodor, Janos
    Geszler
    Glickstalv
    Grueber
    Grunwald
    Gyoki (Dr.)
    Gyszi, Kadar
    Harren
    Heinau
    Horvat, Lipot
    Jabeg
    Jasz, Dezso
    Kafsner
    Kanyy, Hugo
    Kelemen, Lajos
    Korosi, Marietta
    Kraffner
    Langfelder
    Lecher
    Leidenberger
    Lenard, Robert
    Lenki
    Lunzer
    Magyar, Misi
    Manoilescu
    Minnus, István
    Neumann, Janos
    Nizzola
    Nyari, Jeno
    O’ Daniel
    Oppler
    Papházy
    Philipp
    Pollatschek, Eduard
    Popper, H.
    Potok
    Radovski
    Rapuch
    Reuss
    Richter (Dr.)
    Romulus, Brola
    Salminszky
    Sametz
    Schaffler
    Schenker
    Spitzer
    Storwell
    Strobl, Zsiga
    Szaray
    Szego
    Toifel
    Torok, Lajos
    Vajda, Alfred (Dr.)
    Vecsey
    Vest, Baron
    Veszi
    Vidrigi, Stan
    Warga
    Internationale Stickstoffeinigung (International Nitrogen Pact), Lloyd
    Magyar Nitrogen Egyezmeny (Hungarian Nitrogen Pact), Lloyd
    Városrendezes cimszo megirasa a Guttenberg Lexicon szamara (City Planning: for the Guttenberg Lexicon), Christensen
    Zur Lage der Welt-Stickstoffindustrie (On the Situation of the World Nitrogen Industry), Lloyd
    Pozsony szabalyozasi terverol (On the Regulation Plans for Bratislava), Mérnökegylet
    Ganz factory
    Goldberger factory
    Tata-Banhidai Water supply
    The Danube dam and its flood control
  - Journal 15: October 29, 1930 - May 30, 1932 (Box 3)
    The Swiss group steps back from the purchase of the Nitrogen Factory due to the failure of Creditanstalt. After the Nitrogen Factory trial, the Mironescu government falls.
    Nitrogen prices fall in the worldwide market. The International Nitrogen Agreement ends, as does the collective office in London, European Export Company. The Carbide Syndicate survives. The contract with Solvay is renewed.
    The Nitrogen Factory begins to provide electricity to Seta. Imre Forbáth continues to meet with Dr. Hiller and to discuss the possibility of producing bauxite. Forbáth travels to Paris, Munich, Vienna, Zurich, Berlin, and Bucharest.
    Two-thirds of the workers are discharged from the Hungarian office due to the economic crisis. In 1931, the Baustellung Berlin Exhibition invites Forbáth to exhibit his city plans. He prepares plans for Antwerp, Brasso, Zamardi, Belgrade, Birmingham, and Bratislava. The German publication Deutscher Gelehrter Kalender writes about Imre Forbáth in its third edition (1931).
    In 1931, he begins to rewrite the diary he wrote in Russia while prisoner of war. That diary was written in German and in stenography, so it cannot be decoded except by him. The diary in stenography is the eighth diary in the collection.
    Bachler
    Baron, Tomi
    Bence, Gyula
    Bocke, Kalman
    Boni
    Csetenyi, Jozsef
    Dinda
    Fuchs
    Gelderen
    German
    Greiner, Sandor
    Halapy, Oszkar
    Harsanyi, Zsolt
    Henz
    Herceg, Peter
    Kiss (Dr.)
    Kornfeld, Baron
    Kragsner
    Krauss
    Lany, Lajos (Dr.)
    Miller, Pali
    Paloczik
    Partos
    Poposh
    Rapor, Jeno
    Raprey
    Romanescu
    Ropoch
    Rosenbaumne
    Saffer, Misa
    Salusinszky, Gyula
    Sebestyen, Karoly
    Sionovits
    Stockheim
    Szekeres, Margit
    Thomand
    Wehner, Jozsef (Dr.)
    Wittmann, Mihaly
    A modern mutragyagyartas problemai (Problems of Modern Chemical Fertilizer Production), Magyar Szemle
    A mutragya hatasa a Magyar buzara (Effects of Chemical Fertilizer on Hungarian Wheat), For Stiffstoff
    Dualism in Städtebau (Dualism in City Building), Monatshafte, Baukunst and Städtebau
    Hadifogolynaplo (Diary of a Prisoner of War)
    Pozsonyi terv (Plan of Bratislava), Közlöny
    A nemzetkozi Nitrogenkartell Fejlesztese (Expansion of the International Nitrogen Cartel)
    A Pozsonyi terv (Plan of Bratislava), Mérnök Egylet
    Goldberger Factory
    Water supply of Cheora Kadisa Jewish Cemetery
  - Journal 16: May 30, 1932 - March 5, 1934 (Box 3)
    There are great expectations before the Economic Conference in Lausanne, but it does little to improve the situation. It is impossible to escape the economic depression without the cooperation of all European states. Workers have been let go and wages have been cut in Diciosanmartin and at the Budapest office. Sales of calcium cyanamide fertilizers, which have accounted for most sales for the past four to five years, are decreasing. Romanian sales have completely stopped, and Hungarian sales are minimal. The reason for this, besides the bad Hungarian agricultural situation, is the opening of the Fertilizer Factory in Pet, Hungary. On the other hand, sales of calcium carbamide, caustic potash, and electricity have increased. New profitable products include trichloroethylene, tetrachloride, chromates, hydrochloric acid, borax, ultramarine, and nitric acid. The Ministry of War is the biggest customer for nitric acid. Kerbs, a factory owner from Oslo, discusses the production of hydrogen-superoxide with Forbáth. There are also plans to manufacture gas. The Romanian Minister, Citatiune, countersues Forbáth for 1.5 million lei, which Romania has paid to the Nitrogen Factory in the form of coverage for losses.
    The second degree verdict, in favor of Imre Forbáth, declares that Romania is not the successor of the Austro-Hungarian War Ministry. The lawyer defending Romania is Rosenthal; Forbáth’s lawyers are Elias and Juniau. The Factory has to go through another trial, against its delegate, Marcu. There are conferences in Berlin about the rebirth of the Carbide Cartel, and in Paris, about the rebirth of the Calcium Cyanamide Cartel. In Hungary, there are restrictions on Romanian foreign exchange and imports. The office of international common sales, Super Export, is closing. Forbáth’s office in Budapest is moving from 1 Jozsef Square to 7 Dorottya Street. In 1933, the first ever telephone conversation takes place between the Budapest office and Diciosanmartin.
    The Przemysl Monument is unveiled in a square on the Buda side of the Margit Bridge, in memory of the prisoners of war from Przemysl who died in Russian captivity. The statue was given to the capital by Captain Tamássy, and accepted by Vice-Major Liber. The veterans, with General Domokos Lazar, parade in lines of four in front of the monument. The Hungarians advertise a competition for the anthem of Balaton.
    Alerbst
    Bachmann
    Balazs, Peter
    Balogh, Vajda
    Bernstein(Dr.)
    Bock
    Bodin
    Boni, Feri
    Breaud
    Brokwode
    Brunner
    Caurbon, Mario
    Chorin, Ferenc
    Clurik
    Csaszkazy
    Denes, Imre
    Deuts, Lajos
    Deutsch, Erno
    Dottka
    Ekrest
    Erske
    Farkas, Heddi
    Ferenc, Pal
    Fleischer
    Frank
    Frank(Dr.)
    Freger
    Gandilleu
    Gaz
    Gilchrich
    Golderen, Max
    Goldfinger, Leo
    Hevesi (Rabbi)
    Hoffgarten
    Huy
    Karnitz-Fodor
    Kemenyi (Major)
    Kerbs
    Krafsner
    Krebs
    Krepler
    Lajos Nagy
    Lanczi, Boske
    Lang
    Libermann
    Lippay
    Magyar, Mihaly
    Mangold, (Pal)
    Meyer
    Muller, Pal
    Nemes, Olga
    O’ Sebastian
    Ory
    Otvos
    Padovski, Bucher
    Parucz
    Polski
    Polya, Lili
    Poth, Miklos
    Proszerinmier
    Ramitz
    Riddersbuh
    Rittman
    Rodling
    Roman, Aurel
    Rozsa
    Ruckert
    Ruschman
    Russel
    Schenjer, Gyula
    Scherbel
    Schimitzek
    Schonberg, Arnol
    Szekely, Bela
    Szekely, Imre
    Szigeti, Pal
    Terrece
    Tomasi
    Tricher
    Uzonyi, Bela (Dr.)
    Vajda(Dr.)
    Weiss
    Wild
    Wilhelm, Karoly (Dr.)
    Zador, István
    A Taban uj tervei (New Plans of Taban)
    Roma és Parizs tervezeserol (On the Planning of Rome and Paris), Pesti Naplo
    Goldberg Factory
  - Journal 17: March 8, 1934 - February 5, 1936 (Box 3)
    The situation of the nitrogen market is improving in Romania; however, exports are still restricted. There are two new branches in the Nitrogen Factory, for the production of tiles and of synthetic ammonias and their derivatives. In the internal market, the demand for these products is so large that the factory plans to enlarge. The buildings surrounding the factory must also be expanded.
    There are negotiations about the sale of the company to a group of buyers: Pager, Dragonieranu Buzescu, Constantinescu, Gigurtu, and Caramfil. Gigurtu is the Minister of Industry. This group buys the Nitrogen Factory on January 30, 1935. The contract is written by the lawyers Vajda and Domong. Though the Romanian Bank does not give permission for the transaction, negotiations go on. Because of the so called Incadrare Law, other problems arise around the factory. The law breaks up workers and administrators into seven groups. In each group, there can be a maximum of 205 foreigners, meaning Jews and Hungarians. In the group to which the Nitrogen Factory belongs, a ministerial committee has the right to fire anyone and appoint a new official. The ministry immediately fires and expels a Hungarian engineer. Imre Forbáth takes these trials calmly, while Romanian impatience with the Nitrogen Factory increases.
    The case against the Ministry of War takes a new turn: in contrast to the last two verdicts, the highest court of cassation declares the Romanian War Office the successor of the Austro-Hungarian War Office. Forbáth appeals to the Tribunal Arbitral in Paris. Many trials and hearings follow.
    There is a Carbide Cartel conference in Zurich and Rome and a Middle European Nitrogen meeting in Prague and Vienna. There is a Syndicate meeting in Paris. Forbáth sends a representative to the Berlin conference.
    He is upset about the apathy of the world towards the persecution of the Jews. Forbáth is enthusiastic about Thomas Mann’s letter on Nazi Germany, published in the Zürcher Zeitung. Mussolini’s speech is aired on the radio.
    Forbáth visits the Hungarian Tile Factory. In Hungary, Horthy is chancellor and Gyula Gombos prime minister. Anti-Semitism is growing in the country.
    After selling the Nitrogen Factory, Imre Forbáth wants to become a private engineer again. The National Association of Engineers elects him President of City Development in Budapest. He is also a delegate of the City Building Council to the Congress of Civil Engineering.
    Danner (Dr.)
    Domonyi, Bator
    Epressi
    Fauser, Giacomo
    Feher, Pal
    Gigurtu
    Horthy
    Junian
    Kornfeld (Baron)
    Krauu
    Kunz
    Magnus
    Maniu
    Nyari
    Papp
    Schiffer
    Simonkovics
    Sipos
    Toszegi
    Viforeanu
    A Kispesti Munkasnegyed Fotere (Main Square of the Workers’ District in Kispest), Magyar Epitomuveszet
    A Taban rendezesi terve (Organization and Plan of Taban), Self-published, Bucharest; Lloyd
    Wells of the Goldberger Factory in Obuda
    Budafok Plant: Design of the New Water Pump
  - Journal 18: February 6, 1936 - December 21, 1937 (Box 4)
    At the beginning of 1937, the Diciosanmartin Factory is still run by Imre Forbáth from his office in Budapest. After the long controversy with the Romanian government, the Nitrogen Factory is sold to the Romanians. On December 14, 1935, the assembly declares that the company’s seat is being moved to Bucharest. The Budapest office is eliminated on May 1, 1936. After the factory is given to Romania, 14 out of 16 Jewish officials of the factory are fired, and most of the Hungarians as well. Imre Forbáth takes responsibility for the fired officials, allowing them to retire formally, and pays them rewards in the name of the former owners of the factory. Forbáth assigns a Hungarian assistant to the new director appointed by the Romanians.
    The first million lei from the sale of the Nitrogen Factory arrives at the Credit Bank, but the contract signed in 1935 expires without the completion of the purchase. A new contract must be drawn up with Gigortu. The Romanian National Bank takes a long time to approve it.
    Forbáth continues to represent the factory at International Cartel meetings in London, Berlin, and Paris even after it is sold. Before his London trip, Forbáth writes a letter to Samuel Hoare, in which he congratulates him on his book, The Fourth Seal. He would like to arrange a meeting to discuss the possibility of publishing his diary written in Siberia as a prisoner of war. Hoare replies warmly and invites him to London. Imre Forbáth arrives in London at the moment when Hoare is named First Lord of Admiralty, so their meeting has to be postponed.
    A competition is announced for plans for the exhibition and market area in Vienna. Forbáth draws up a plan with the engineers Deli and Farago. They take third place, the only foreign plan given an award.
    A group from the Commerce Bank negotiates with the Hungarian Government about the rental of the Port Authority in Csepel, with Forbáth joining the discussions. He is a leading figure of the Chamber of Engineers and of the press, involved in providing medical care and insurance to engineers. He wants to go back to teaching at the newly reorganized Technological University in Budapest.
    Achner
    Bachler, Lenke
    Balogh, Jozsi
    Bence
    Benes, Imre
    Berczlettig
    Berzenczey
    Bold, Adel
    Boldizsar
    Czako (Dr.)
    Czako, Bela
    Domony (Dr.)
    Drogomiennu
    Eggel
    Elek, Kato
    Engl (Dr.)
    Erdelyi, Natan
    Farkas, Naci
    Fenyes, Adolf
    Gal
    Gluckstal
    Gold, Frigyes
    Halom, Margit
    Heltay, Jozsef
    Horthy, István
    Hubert
    Karzate
    Marcselenyi
    Mery, Imre
    Mihailich
    Mihailik, Frigyes
    Morgesianu
    Okanyi, Andor
    Pap, Ferenc
    Popper, Gyorgy
    Quirin
    Ravasz, Laszlo
    Revai
    Richter, Gedeon
    Ritz
    Rohringer
    Salusinszky
    Schuller
    Simoncsics
    Szabo, Bela
    Szabo, Gusztav
    Szeben, Dezso
    Ubul
    Vajda, András
    Vajda, György
    Valentin
    Ver, Tibor
    Wertner, Richard
    Wicklin
    Wigner
    Wittenberg
    Presentations of this period:
    Bukarest ujjaepitese (Reconstruction of Bucharest)
    Vilagkiallitas Parizsban (World Fair in Paris)
    Expert for the Capital’s Waterworks Directory
    Extension of the Waterworks in Buda
    Pumps of the Goldberger Factory at the Danube
    Water Supply and Sewage in Újvidék
  - Journal 19:: December 21, 1937 - November 11, 1939 (Box 4)
    Imre Forbáth goes to Berlin for the first Carbide Cartel meeting. On the way back, he stops at Vienna, where he sees swastikas and Nazi banners everywhere. The synagogue is burned down and Jewish stores are vandalized and marked.
    The Nitrogen Factory’s February 15, 1938 meeting declares the factory’s worth to be 11 million pengős. After the company is sold, the main office is relocated to Bucharest. Forbáth donates the factory’s old plans to the Technical Museum of Budapest.
    British Oxygen tries to dictate conditions for the carbide market. The second Cartel meeting ends in Paris. The meeting of the third Cartel is planned for Geneva on July 1, 1938. Imre Forbáth goes to this meeting with his seventeen-year-old son, Tamás. Afterwards, Imre goes to Paris while Tamás goes to London, where he takes an examination in English at the City of London College.
    In the Technical University in Budapest, a National Drinking Water Conference is held and the National Common Health Institute is established. The World Fair opens, and an International Eucharistic Congress is held at the same time as the St. István Exhibition. Cardinal Pacelli leads the procession into Budapest, at the side of Horthy.
    Keren Kajemeth’s representative seeks out Forbáth to collect money for the purchase of Palestinian lands. Jewish refugees from Austria and Germany ask for Forbáth’s help. Emigration from the country is more and more frequent.